Register of the Mark Roberti collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Mark Roberti collection
1967-1994
97007
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize boxes (4.0 linear feet)
Dispatches, reports, memoranda, and sound recordings relating to negotiations and plans for the transfer of Hong Kong from British to Chinese sovereignty. Includes photocopies of United States State Department documents released under the Freedom of Information Act; drafts of the Basic Law of Hong Kong; and recordings of interviews of British and Chinese officials. Used as research material for Mark Roberti's book, The Fall of Hong Kong: China's Triumph and Britain's Betrayal (New York, 1996).
Roberti, Mark,
Access
Box 4 closed until 2027 June 30. The remainder of the collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1997.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical note
Mark Roberti is a former Hong Kong correspondent for Asia Week. He arrived in Hong Kong in 1984, the year the Sino-British Joint Declaration was signed. Roberti wrote the book The Fall of Hong Kong: China’s Triumph and Britain’s Betrayal (New York, 1996), based on the materials in the collection.
Scope and Content of Collection
Containes dispatches, reports, memoranda, and sound recordings relating to negotiations and plans for the transfer of Hong Kong from British to Chinese sovereignty. Includes photocopies of United States State Department documents released under the Freedom of Information Act; drafts of the Basic Law of Hong Kong; and recordings of interviews of British and Chinese officials. Used as research material for Mark Roberti's book The Fall of Hong Kong: China's Triumph and Britain's Betrayal (New York, 1994).
United States. Dept. of State.; China--Foreign relations--Great Britain.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--China.; Hong Kong (China)--History--Transfer of Sovereignty from Great Britain, 1997.; Hong Kong (China)--Politics and government.; Phonotapes.
- Briefing paper, 1980-1988 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Correspondence, 1979-1994
  - 1979, 1982, 1984 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - 1988 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - 1989 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - 1990 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - 1992 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - 1993-1994 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Correspondence released in 1993 (Box-folder 1: 8)
- Department of State Executive Secretariat Action Slips, 1988-1990, 1997 (Box-folder 1: 9)
- List of Appeals Panel Members, undated (Box-folder 1: 10)
- Memoranda, 1966, 1988, 1990 (Box-folder 1: 11)
- Press Releases and News Reporting, 1980-1984 (Box-folder 1: 12)
- Telegrams, 1978-1990
  - 1978-1979 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - 1982 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - 1983 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - 1984 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - 1985-1987 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - 1988 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - January - May, 1989 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - June - July, 1989 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - August - December, 1989 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - 1990 (Box-folder 3: 4)
- Speeches and Writings, circa 1967-1990
  - "The Confrontation in Hong Kong: Its Past and Its Future,", 16 November, 1967 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Hong Kong Constitution, undated (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Hong Kong's Reversion to China, undated (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - "Indochinese Refugees: Protection, Care, And Processing Can Be Improved,", 19 August, 1980 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Vietanamese Refugees, 1988-1990 (Box-folder 3: 9)
- Sound recordings on compact sound cassettes, circa 1967-1991 (Box 5-7)
  Scope and Content
  Includes 100 compact sound cassettes documenting various conferences, research notes, and interviews.
  - Akers-Jones, David
  - Anderson, Donald
  - Bottomley, David
  - Boyo, John
  - Broadfoot, Bob
  - Bray, Dennis
  - Cater, Jack, (Part 1 and 2)
  - Cathay Pacific Execus
  - Cha, Louis
  - Chan, Darwin
  - Chan, John
  - Chan, Thomas
  - Chang, Dennis
  - Chang, S. Y., (Part 1 and 2)
  - Chen, Albert
  - Cheong, Stephen
  - Cheng, Kai-nam,(Part 1 and 2)
  - Cheng, Y. P.
  - Chow, Selina
  - Cradock, (Part 1 and 2)
  - Dubbs, Alf
  - Ehrman, William, (Part 1 and 2), 27 November, 1991
  - Fanshawe, Lord
  - Foulkes, George
  - Fung, K. K.
  - Galsnorthy
  - Glenarthur
  - Gordon, Sidney
  - Ho, Albert, 3 December, 1991
  - Howe, Geoffrey
  - Howe, Geoffrey, Press Conference, 3 May, 1988
  - Huang, Rayson, (Part 1 and 2)
  - Jayawickrama, N.
  - Kan, Y. K., (Part 1 and 2)
  - Kwong, K. C.
  - Kwong, Peter
  - Lai, Jimmy
  - Lee, Allen
  - Lee, David
  - Lee, Martin, circa 1991
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes 6 compact sound cassette tapes.
  - Lee, Q. W., (Part 1 and 2)
  - Lee, Wing-tat
  - Leong, Ernest
  - Li, Qingsen
  - Li, Simon
  - Liang, Raymond
  - Liu, Dorothy
  - Lo, T. S.
  - Lo, Vincent, (Part 1, 2 and 3)
  - Lobo, Roger
  - Luce, Richard
  - Luk, Michael, December 10, 1991
  - MacLehose
  - MacPhearson
  - Man, Archie
  - Margolis, (Part 1 and 2)
  - McGregor, Jimmy
  - McLaren
  - Newbigging, David
  - Notes, 1967
  - Parr, Chris and Small, Frank
  - Paul, Alan
  - Parashar, P. N.
  - Shaddey, William
  - Shive, Glenn
  - Szeto, Wah, (Part 1 and 2)
  - Tam, Yiu-chung
  - Tang, K. N.
  - Telford, John
  - Theodoulou
  - Walden, (Part 1 and 4)
  - Weloow, Peter
  - Wilson, David
  - Wong, Patrick
  - Wong, Po-yan
  - Wu, Raymond, (Part 1 and 2)